Guide to the New-York Historical Society General Correspondence 1805-2024 (bulk, 1805-1982) NYHS-RG 2
New-York Historical Society
- Series V. Topical Correspondence, 1846-1985; 2.29 Linear feet in seven document boxes
  - Requests for "Reproductions of Famous Historical Personages & Scenes" letters (7 folders), 1928-1939 (Box 356, Folder 1-7)
    Folders 1-6 consists of letters from teachers, students, and others requesting the illustrations provided free of charge by the N-YHS entitled "Reproductions of Famous Historical Personages & Scenes." Folder 7 contains correspondence written to the N-YHS from various individuals in regard to the value of a newspaper published in Kingston, NY on January 4, 1800 of the "Ulster Gazette" (Num. 88 Vol. II) that contains an account of the death of Washington. Box 357 contains several hundred index cards requesting "Reproductions of Famous Historical Personages & Scenes" from schools across the country.
  - Requests for "Reproductions of Famous Historical Personages & Scenes" postcards, 1928-1939 (Box 357, Cards -)
    These postcards were submitted to the N-YHS from various schools and organizations requesting to be sent the illustrations from "Reproductions of Famous Historical Personages & Scenes."
  - Thompson Property at East Hampton, Long Island, 1941-1946 (Box 355, Folder 1-9)
    Materials include the title to the Thompson East Hampton property; Bank of New York documentation of closing and deed on property; real estate transactions between J. Edward Gay Jr., and the Weekes Brothers; policy of insurance from the Title Guarantee and Trust Company and other insurance documentation; extensive correspondence between the Village of East Hampton and N-YHS exempting N-YHS from tax payments on property; correspondence related to the maintenance of the property; correspondence between various realtors and Arthur Sutherland, Esq. in regard to setting the asking price the property in 1946; final sale of property contract to Ivan Barrington White; photo reproduction created by Garrett H. Winter (Superintendent, N-YHS) showing detailed second and third floor plans of house; photo reproduction of map of property showing area and scale of property as surveyed by Theodore F. Squires (Licensed Land Surveyor); Statement of Apportionments; letter from Nelson C. Osborne (Insurance and Real Estate Notary Public) recommending three principal local real estate brokers as: J. Edward Gay Jr., Edward T. Dayton, and James M. Strong; correspondence between Columbia University and N-YHS discussing the wish of Sarah D. Gardiner (niece of Charles, Elizabeth and Mary Thompson) to acquire several books, an etching, and flowers; various insurance policies including fire and war damage; correspondence between Frank Howe to A.J.Wall (Director, N-YHS) with regard to house maintenance (plumbing, heating), visitors to the estate (students, Girl Scout Troops, Mother's Club), donations, and other matters; responses to invitation to attend the dedication of the Thompson Homestead Memorial on July 25, 1942; estimates for plumbing and re-roofing of the estate; letter confirming Frank Howe and his wife as caretakers of the East Hampton homestead at $90 per month; bills for gas and laundry; correspondence with Long Island Lighting Company in regard to proposed extension of gas facilities on the property; information on the estate and Mr. Charles G. Thompson received from J. Custis Lawrence; correspondence between A.J.Wall (Director, N-YHS) and Nelson C. Osborne (Realtor); correspondence with regard to house maintenance, hours of operation, weather reports, salary checks received, and visitors; reports on the Thompson house sent to A.J. Wall from Mr. H. Winter; letter informing staff of closing the house during the winter months; 1944 announcement published in East Hampton Star of exhibitions at the Thompson Homestead; several letters exchanged between Katherine Wellenkamp (Curator) and Donald A. Shelley (Curator of Paintings and Acting Museum Curator) and other staff on her experience at the homestead and attendance records, as well as an invitation to the Society's Strawberry Festival; letters exchanged between Shelley and Wellenkamp of the tensions between her and the caretakers (Mr. and Mrs. Testa); letter to Zabriskie from Testa in regard to the tensions between the caretakers and Wellenkamp; several letters exchanged between Jeannette Edwards Rattray (East Hampton Star) and N-YHS staff in regard to advertising the museum; exhibition brochure sent to the East Hampton Star for publication; lecture given by Susan E. Lyman, "Shopping in Old New York"; several letters between E.H.Braem (Mothers' Club) and N-YHS in regard to a lecture on New York people from 1626-1943; request for N-YHS to take part in a parade along with the Ladies Village Improvement Society of East Hampton; requests for permission for Wellenkamp's sister to stay with her at the home for a few weeks during the summer; visit from two Satterthwaite sisters who had spent their childhood in the original house built in 1873 by their father who sold the estate to the Thompson family and their donation of three spoons dug up on the property from Native American graves when the house was being erected; letter from the F.A. Bartlett Tree Expert Company in regard to the condition of trees on the property; letters to Wellenkamp and Testa (caretaker) informing them that the N-YHS Board of Trustees voted to permanently close the Thompson Homestead Memorial in May 1946; letters to lighting and coal companies to discontinue service as property was sold; brochure of the Thompson Homestead Memorial containing a brief history and summary of each exhibition room; 1943 brochure of exhibition: Things Military Through the Years (1750-1898); list of household goods from Thompson Homestead sold to N-YHS staff members upon closing of museum; hand written records of attendance for the Thompson Homestead taken between the dedication opening on July 25, 1942 and October 8, 1945.
  - U.S.Treasury Department-Tax Exempt Material, 1926-1985 (Box 359, Folder 1)
    Includes application for tax-exempt status; several letters appear to be annual rulings by the Treasury Department for tax-exempt status of the N-YHS; letter dated June 22, 1926 from the office of the Commissioner of Internal Revenue in regard to taxable status under the provisions of Section 231 (6) of the Revenue Act of 1926; ruling relative to the deductibility on the income tax return for 1924 filed by Samuel V. Hoffman of contributions made to the N-YHS; letters dated August 22, 1967 from U.S. Treasury Department discussing contributions made to the N-YHS by individual donors; requests for N-YHS to submit to Treasury Department documents such as affidavits as to its purpose, activities, the character of the organization, and financial statements showing the sources of its income, along with the institution's charter or articles of incorporation and by-laws; copy of Revenue Ruling 67-246 I.R.B. 1967-32,4 (allowance of deductions); supporting documents submitted by N-YHS to obtain a ruling that the Society was "publicly supported; letter dated December 24, 1985 that shows that the Date of Exemption Letter was created April 1938 (exemption in April 1938 pursuant to 1954 Code section 501(c) (3) or its predecessor Code Section).
  - Miscellaneous Matter (6 folders), circa 1868-1937, undated (Box 359, Folder 2-7)
    Includes a few miscellaneous notes, clippings, lists, object photographs, photo reproductions of the "rag-man" and other solicitation advertisements; print matter; business and calling cards; and personal correspondence.
  - Act of Incorporation (2 folders), 1846-1973 (Box 359, Folder 8-9)
  - Education and Public Relations (5 folders), 1958-1965 (Box 360, Folder 1-5)
  - Bella Landauer-related correspondece, 1932-1960 (Box 360, Folder 9)
    Holds a few letters related to the Landauer collection.